Guide to the Jennings Photograph Collection [1858]-1957 PR 135
New-York Historical Society
Jennings Photograph Collection
[1858]-1957
New-York Historical Society
PR 135
12.5 Linear feet (13 boxes)
Collection of albums, book manuscripts, scrapbooks, photographic prints, postcards, and negatives realting to the family and career of Arthur Bates Jennings, primarily compiled by his son Dr. Edward Allen Jennings.
Provenance
The collection is comprised of two separate gifts from Mrs. William Kenoe, on January 26 and March 9, 1959.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to thirty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. See guidelines in Print Room for details.
Biographical Note
Arthur Bates Jennings (1849-1927) was a New York City architect, who received his A.B. in 1870 from the College of the City of New York. He trained under such notable architects as George B. Post and Russell Sturgis, and set up his first independent office around 1876 at 71 Broadway. Early in his career, he worked mostly on residential designs; later he moved on to designs of public buildings, specializing in churches, but also working on buildings for colleges, universities, and a few private companies. Jennings moved his office several times, but always maintained a presence in lower Manhattan between the years 1876 and 1919. His business address at the time of his retirement in 1919 was 253 Broadway. While much of Jennings' early professional work was done in the New York City region, beginning in the 1890s, his multi-turreted churches and other public buildings were constructed across the United States, from Portland, Maine to Seattle, Washington.
Arthur Jennings married Caroline Jerusha Allen of West Meriden, Connecticut; the couple had three children: Edward Allen Jennings (1882-1958), Arthur B. Jennings, Jr., and Helen Bates Jennings. Arthur Jennings, Jr., became a professional organist, choirmaster, and instructor, eventually becoming a full professor at the University of Minnesota.
Dr. Edward Allen Jennings attended Wesleyan University and Columbia University's College of Physicians and Surgeons, receiving his medical degree in 1913. Dr. Jennings served on the staffs of Harlem, Fordham, and St. Luke's Hospitals in New York, was a First Lieutenant in the Army Medical Corps during World War I, and had an established medical practice in New York City. Dr. Jennings was an avid amateur historian, and researched and wrote on church architecture, local history, and his father's architectural career. He penned several book manuscripts, such as his Manhattanville: An Architectural Retrospective, which were never published. Dr. Jennings continued to practice medicine until his death in 1958.
Scope and Content Note
The Jennings Photograph Collection spans the period from circa 1858 through 1957 and contains photographs, postcards, book manuscripts, scrapbooks, and albums relating to the architectural work, professional careers, interests, and personal lives of members of the family of architect Arthur Bates Jennings. Most of the materials in the collection were gathered or compiled by Dr. Edward A. Jennings, and they reflect many of his professional and personal interests. Dr. Jennings, primarily a medical doctor, was also an amateur architectural historian and local history enthusiast. His interests are reflected in scrapbooks and book manuscripts incorporating photographs, postcards, news clippings, maps, and accompanying descriptive commentary addressing the architectural career of his father, church architecture, Short Hills, NJ, and the history of various west side neighborhoods of New York City. Additional scrapbooks relate to Dr. Jennings' own career and education; one scrapbook relates to the career of Arthur B. Jennings, Jr., a professional organist and professor. The remainder of the collection consists of photographs of various Jennings family members as well as members of the Allen family of Meriden, Connecticut, the family of Carolina Jerusha Allen Jennings.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into five series:
Missing Title
Church Designs also Residence and College Buildings by Arthur B. Jennings, F.A.I.A.
Church Architecture
Manhattan Architecture and History
Short Hills and Summit, NJ
Jennings Family
Related Material at the New-York Historical Society
The Jennings Photograph Collection was removed from the Architect and Engineer File (PR-003). The Jennings Family Papers are available in the Manuscript Department of the New-York Historical Society Library. Additional materials, including a manuscript copy of Manhattanville: An Architectural Retrospective, by Dr. Edward A. Jennings, are available in the Special Collections Department of Manhattanville College Library in the Edward A. Jennings Collection.
Clippings (information artifacts); Cartes-de-visite (card photographs); Albumen prints.; Group portraits.; Washington Heights (New York, N.Y.); Summit (N.J.) -- History.; Scrapbooks.; Short Hills (N.J.) -- History.; Manhattanville (New York, N.Y.) -- History.; New York (N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc.; New York (N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; Medical students -- New York (State) -- New York.; Hospitals -- New York (State) -- New York -- Staff -- Portraits.; Dwellings -- United States -- Pictorial works.; College buildings -- United States -- Pictorial works.; Church buildings -- United States -- Pictorial works.; Architecture -- United States -- Pictorial works.; Albums (books); Cabinet photographs.; Photographic prints.; negatives (photographs); Portraits.; Postcards.; Programs (documents); Sheet music.; Harlem Hospital Center (New York, N.Y.); Jennings family; Jennings, Arthur Bates, 1849-1927; Jennings, Arthur Bates, Jr.; Jennings, Caroline Allen -- Portraits; Jennings, Edward Allen, 1881-1958; St. Luke's Hospital (New York, N.Y.); Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.); Allen (Family); Columbia University. College of Physicians and Surgeons; Cushing Academy; Fordham Hospital
- Series I: Church Designs also Residence and College Buildings by Arthur B. Jennings, F.A.I.A.
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I consists of three slightly different copies of a book manuscript with mounted photographs, postcards, correspondence and commentary by Edward A. Jennings about the buildings and career of Arthur B. Jennings. The three copies are nearly identical, but a few differences exist; volume two holds more original correspondence than the other volumes, and building coverage differs slightly in each of the volumes as noted in the box listing. The book was never published. A list of buildings depicted is available in the box listing under the first copy; only the differences from copy one have been noted under copies two and three. Three folders of duplicate prints from the volumes are available at the end of the series.
  Photographs are arranged in book manuscripts in their original order. They are listed here alphabetically by state, city and building name. The volume in box 1 includes a page index at the end of the volume. Dates indicate date of each building's erection, not the date the photograph was taken.
  - Church Designs also Residence and College Buildings by Arthur B. Jennings, F.A.I.A. [Copy 1; the following buildings are depicted:]
    - Connecticut
      - Meriden -- All Saints Memorial Protestant Episcopal Church, 1892-1893 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - Waterbury -- Bunker Hill Congregational Church [competition sketch], undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - Winsted -- First Congregational Church, 1900-1901 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - Winsted -- Second Congregational Church, 1898-1899 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
    - Maine
      - Portland -- St. Lawrence Congregational Church, 1896-1897 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
    - Michigan
      - Olivet -- Burrage Memorial Library, Olivet College, 1890 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
    - New Jersey
      - Bloomfield -- Westminster Presbyterian Church, 1890-1892 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - East Orange -- Dod, S. Bayard Residence, 1885 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - New Brunswick -- Presbyterian Church [reconstruction after 1888 fire] (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - Newark -- First Reformed Church, 1898 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - Seabright -- Low, Joseph T., residence [interiors and exteriors], [1883] (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - Short Hills -- Cleveland, A.L., residence, undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - Short Hills -- Jennings, Arthur B. residence [later A.E. Banning residence], 1880-1881 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - Short Hills -- Bliss residence, undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - Summit -- Allen, John Platt, residence, [1870-1879] (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - Summit -- Simmons, H.E., residence, [1870-1879] (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - Summit -- Vernon, P.H., residence, 1878 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - Summit -- Sommers, D., residence, undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
    - New York
      - Ballston Spa -- First Baptist Church, 1896 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - Bay Shore -- Gunther, William H., residence, [1887] (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - Chatham -- First Reformed Church, 1901 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - Dunkirk -- First Methodist Episcopal Church, 1916 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - New York City -- 21--49 45th Road, Long Island City, Queens, 1891 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - New York City -- Cathedral of St. John the Divine, photograph of perspective sketch by Arthur B. Jennings submitted for competition in 1888-1889, undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - New York City -- Clay, George Everson, residence -- 167 11th St., now Edgewood Reformed Church, Brooklyn, 1902-1904 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - New York City -- Hanover Fire Insurance Co. Building, 34 Pine St., 1893 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - New York City -- Jennings, Arthur B., residence -- 136th St. and Broadway, 1886-1887 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - New York City -- Neresheimer, E. August, residence -- 119th St. and Lenox Ave., 1886 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - New York City -- Residences -- 137--145 West 87th St., 1884-1887 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - New York City -- Residences -- 139--143 West 94th St., 1885-1886 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - New York City -- Residences -- 72nd St. and Tenth Ave., 1886-1888 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - New York City -- Sherman, Stephen F., residence -- Riverside Dr. near 113th St., 1883-1885 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - New York City -- Union Presbyterian Church of Bay Ridge, Brooklyn, 1896 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - New York City -- Warner, Dr. Lucien C., residence -- 126th St. and Fifth Ave., 1882-1883 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - New York City -- Webb Institute of Naval Architecture, 1890-1893 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - Penn Yan -- First Methodist Episcopal Church, undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - Saratoga Springs -- New England Congregational Church, 1900 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - Sea Cliff -- Whitlock residence, [1876] (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
    - Ohio
      - Massillon -- St. Timothy's Protestant Episcopal Church, 1893-1898 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - Oberlin -- Warner Hall, Oberlin College, 1883-1884 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
    - Pennsylvania
      - Connellsville -- Baptist Church, 1901 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - Washington -- Gymnasium, Washington & Jefferson College, 1892-1893 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
    - Rhode Island
      - Providence --Cranston St. Baptist Church, 1891-1893 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
    - Virginia
      - Charlottesville -- First Baptist Church, 1904 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - Norfolk-- First Baptist Church, 1909-1910 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
      - Richmond -- Grace Baptist Church, 1898 (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
    - Washington
      - Seattle -- Hotel Denny, undated (Offsite-box 1, Box 1)
  - [Copy 2; same as copy 1 except with no index and the following additional buildings:]
    - Arkansas
      - Hot Springs -- Central Methodist Episcopal Church, 1908 (Offsite-box 2, Box 2)
    - Maine
      - Gardiner -- Congregational Church, undated (Offsite-box 2, Box 2)
    - New York
      - New York City--Bedford Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, 1897 (Offsite-box 2, Box 2)
      - New York City--Riverside Drive, residences south of 122nd St., 1886 (Offsite-box 2, Box 2)
      - New York City--Residences, St. Nicholas Ave., 146th through 148th Sts., 1889-1890 (Offsite-box 2, Box 2)
    - Ohio
      - Oberlin -- Rice Hall, Oberlin College, 1909-1910 (Offsite-box 2, Box 2)
  - [Copy 3; same as copy 1 with no index and the following additional buildings:]
    - New York
      - New York City -- Riverside Drive, residences south of 122nd St., 1886 (Offsite-box 3, Box 3)
    - Ohio
      - Oberlin -- Rice Hall, Oberlin College, 1909-1910 (Offsite-box 3, Box 3)
    - 1-3, Duplicate prints (Offsite-box 3, Box 3)
- Series II: Church Architecture
  Series II. Church Architecture consists of an album compiled by Edward A. Jennings, comprised of postcard views of churches and chapels across the United States. A few of the postcard views in this album are of churches designed by his father, Arthur B. Jennings, but the vast majority simply reflect his wide-ranging interest in the design and structure of churches across the United States.
  Postcards remain in original order in the album; they are listed here alphabetically by state and city for the researcher's convenience.
  - Album of postcard views of the following:
    - Connecticut
      - Farmington -- First Congregational Church (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
      - Hartford --St. Joseph's Cathedral (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
      - Hartford -- Trinity College Chapel (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
      - Litchfield -- St. Michaels Episcopal Church (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
      - Meriden -- St. Rose's Church (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
      - Plymouth -- Congregational Church (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
      - Torrington -- Trinity Episcopal Church (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
      - Winsted -- Methodist Episcopal Church (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
      - Winsted -- St. James Episcopal Church (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
      - Winsted -- St. Joseph's Roman Catholic Church (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
      - Winsted -- 4 miscellaneous town views (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
    - Delaware
      - Claymont -- Church of the Ascension (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
    - Georgia
      - Savannah -- Independent Presbyterian Church (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
    - Maine
      - Portland -- Immanuel Baptist Church (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
    - Massachusetts
      - Ashburnham -- Methodist Church (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
      - Fitchburg -- New C.C. Church (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
      - Great Barrington -- St. Peter's Catholic Church (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
      - Williamtown -- Thompson Memorial Chapel, Williams College (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
    - Minnesota
      - Minneapolis -- Plymouth Congregational Church (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
    - New Jersey
      - Bloomfield -- Westminster Presbyterian Church (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
      - New Brunswick -- First Presbyterian Church (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
      - New Brunswick -- Kirkpatrick Chapel, Rutgers College (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
      - Summit -- Central Presbyterian Church (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
    - New York
      - Ballston Spa -- First Baptist Church (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
      - Brooklyn -- Unidentified Church (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
      - Montgomery -- First Presbyterian Church (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
      - New York --Broadway Tabernacle (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
      - New York -- Church of Paulist Fathers (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
      - New York -- Grace Church (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
      - New York -- St. Thomas Episcopal Church (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
      - New York -- Trinity Church (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
      - Penn Yan -- Methodist Church (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
      - Poughkeepsie -- Vasser College Chapel (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
    - Pennsylvania
      - Carlisle -- Allison Methodist Episcopal Church (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
      - Carlisle -- First Presbyterian Church (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
      - Gettysburg -- Presbyterian Church (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
      - Pittsburgh -- East Liberty Presbyterian Church (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
      - Sewickley -- St. Stephen Episcopal Church and Parish House (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
    - Vermont
      - Montpelier -- Christ Church (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
    - Virginia
      - Charlottesville -- First Baptist Church (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
      - Norfolk -- First Baptist Church (Offsite-box 4, Box 4)
- Series III: Manhattan Architecture and History
  Series III. Manhattan Architecture and History consists primarily of unpublished book manuscripts with mounted photographs and clippings compiled and written by Dr. Edward A. Jennings on the history and architecture of Manhattanville, but also includes photographs and other materials relating to the Manhattan neighborhoods of Morningside Heights, Washington Heights, and the Upper West Side of Manhattan. The Manhattanville volumes were written by Dr. Jennings around 1940, incorporating research he did at the New York City Department of Records and his collection of historical photographs of the area straddling Manhattan Street (which was renamed West 125th Street in 1920). Included are descriptions of the history and landscape of the area along with depictions of local residences, including the Jennings family home, and such neighborhood institutions as Manhattan College, St. Joseph's Roman Catholic Church, the D.F. Tiemann & Co. Color Works, the Dolly Varden Railroad Manhattanville Station, Knickerbocker Hospital, and St. Mary's Church. Copy photographs of lithographs, drawings, and maps are included in the volumes.
  The remaining materials in this series depict buildings in Morningside Heights, including Columbia University, in Washington Heights near Dr. Jennings' home at the time of his death at 2 Pinehurst Avenue, and a few buildings on the Upper West Side. Also included are notes for a slide lecture on the history of Harsenville and Bloomingdale, the current Upper West Side of Manhattan.
  Materials are arranged by Manhattan neighborhood and thereunder alphabetically by subject.
  - Manhattanville
    - Manhattanville: An Architectural Retrospective by E. Allen Jennings,[Two unpublished book manuscripts with mounted photographs], 1940 (Offsite-box 5, Box 5)
    - [Album on history of Manhattanville], [1940] (Offsite-box 6, Box 6, Folder unknown container)
    - Churches and religious institutions, 1906-[1940], undated (Offsite-box 6, Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Institutions and Commercial Businesses, 1903-[1940], undated (Offsite-box 6, Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Residences, 1905-[1940], undated (Offsite-box 6, Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Views, undated (Offsite-box 6, Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Morningside Heights
    - Buildings and views, 1910-1955 (Offsite-box 6, Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Upper West Side
    - Apthorpe Mansion, 91st St. and Ninth Ave., undated (Offsite-box 6, Box 6, Folder 10)
    - "Architecture of Harsenville and Old Bloomingdale" slide lecture outline by E.A. Jennings, [1951-1956] (Offsite-box 6, Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Washington Heights
    - Buildings and views, 1905-[1940], undated (Offsite-box 6, Box 6, Folder 12)
      General note
      See also: Oversize, Box 13, Folder 69
- Series IV: Short Hills and Summit, NJ
  Series IV. consists one scrapbook including a few clippings, maps, and photographs relating to Short Hills and nearby Summit, New Jersey where the Jennings family lived on Highland Avenue between 1881 and 1886 in a house of Arthur B. Jennings' design. Jennings also designed many of the houses in this planned suburban area, including a few belonging to family members in Summit. Several photographs of the Jennings home with the family gathered on the porch are present, along with a simple street map and an obituary concerning the death of the suburb's founder and planner, Stewart Hartshorn. Two original A. B. Jennings sketches of Short Hills houses he designed are included with the folder of Short Hills residences. Loose photographs from the collection depicting architecture in Short Hills and Summit are included in folders following the scrapbook.
  - [Scrapbook], 1886-[1949] (Offsite-box 7, Box 7, Folder unknown container)
  - Short Hills -- Map, undated (Offsite-box 7, Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Short Hills --Residences, 1942, undated (Offsite-box 7, Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Summit -- Residences, 1939, undated (Offsite-box 7, Box 7, Folder 15)
- Series V: Jennings Family
  Series V. Jennings Family consists of photographs and albums documenting the family and professional life of Dr. Edward Jennings, including his siblings, parents, and extended family. Formal photographs portray a variety of Jennings and Allen family members. Albums relate to Dr. Jennings' medical career, education, and extracurricular activities at Wesleyan and Columbia Universities. Photographs of Dr. Jennings with ambulances and staff from Fordham and Harlem Hospitals are included. One album pertains to Arthur Bates Jennings, Jr.' s career as an organist; it contains photographs, sheet music of works composed by Jennings, church bulletins and programs for performances. A family album holds informal snapshots of members of the Jennings family in a variety of settings. Oversize photographs at the end are primarily group portraits from hospitals and schools with which Dr. Edward Jennings was associated.
  Photographs are arranged in three subseries: photographs, negatives, and albums. Thereunder they are filed alphabetically by sitter or group. Oversize group portraits are filed at the end of the series.
  - Photographs
    - Allen, Edward Chauncey, 1858, undated (Offsite-box 8, Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Allen, Edward Linsley, 1886, undated (Offsite-box 8, Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Allen, George William, Mary and family, 1885-1902, undated (Offsite-box 8, Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Allen, John Platt and family, 1885-[1926], undated (Offsite-box 8, Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Allen, Mary Constance, [1892]-1897 (Offsite-box 8, Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Allen, Sarah Hillard Linsley, 1858, undated (Offsite-box 8, Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Allen family, undated (Offsite-box 8, Box 8, Folder 22)
      See also: Oversize, Box 13, Folder 70
    - Jennings, Arthur Bates (1849-1927), [1890]-1925 (Offsite-box 8, Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Jennings, Arthur B., Jr., [1888]-1930, undated (Offsite-box 8, Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Jennings, Caroline Allen, 1897, undated (Offsite-box 8, Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Jennings, Edward Allen--Portraits, 1882-1918, undated (Offsite-box 8, Box 8, Folder 26)
    - Jennings, Edward Allen--Group portraits, school and professional, 1901-1913 (Offsite-box 8, Box 8, Folder 27)
      See also: Oversize -- Box 13, Folders 64--68
    - Jennings, Helen Bates, 1886 (Offsite-box 8, Box 8, Folder 28)
    - Jennings Family -- Miscellaneous, undated (Offsite-box 8, Box 8, Folder 29)
    - Group Portraits, 1886-1912, undated (Offsite-box 8, Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Negatives
    - Group Portraits, 1911 Mar, undated (Offsite-box 8, Box 8, Folder 31-32)
      8 x 10 in. negatives
    - Group Portraits, undated (Offsite-box 9, Box 9, Folder 33-41)
      3.5 x 4 in. negatives
    - Portraits, unidentified, undated (Offsite-box 9, Box 9, Folder 42-46)
    - Views, miscellaneous, undated (Offsite-box 9, Box 9, Folder 47-58)
      3.5 x 4 in. and 5 x 3.5 in. negatives
    - Original negative envelope, undated (Offsite-box 9, Box 9, Folder unknown container)
  - Albums
    - Jennings family photographs, [1900-1915] (Offsite-box 9, Box 9)
    - Jennings, Arthur B., Jr., 1920-1951, undated (Offsite-box 10, Box 10, Folder unknown container)
    - Jennings, Edward Allen [disbound scrapbook pages], [1903-1957] (Offsite-box 11, Box 11, Folder 59-63)
  - Oversize Group Portraits
    - Columbia University, 1911-1914 (Offsite-box 12, Box 12, Folder 64)
    - Cushing Academy (Ashburnham, Massachusetts), 1900-1902 (Offsite-box 12, Box 12, Folder 65)